Guide to the Grace and Max Granich Papers and Photographs TAM.255
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Grace and Max Granich Papers and Photographs
1920s-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Granich, Grace, 1895-1971
Granich, Max, 1896-1987
McDermott, John
Walker, Gina Luria, 1942-
Donefer, Eugene
Donefer, Vera
Nestle, Marion
TAM.255
1.75 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 2 manuscript boxes
Grace Granich was the secretary for Earl Browder, the head of the Communist Party, USA. In the 1930s, she traveled to the Soviet Union and to Shanghai, China, where she served as a liaison to Chinese radicals, notably Agnes Smedley. She also edited The Voice of China (her husband Max Granich was its publisher), the organ of the League for National Salvation, headed by Mme. Sun Yat Sen. During World War II she headed Intercontinent News, a Communist Party news agency. Max (Manny) Granich was the younger brother of writer Michael Gold and served as chauffeur to Earl Browder. Following World War II, the Graniches distanced themselves from the CPUSA and in 1946 founded Higley Hill Camp (Wilmington, Vermont), a left-wing summer camp for children, which they ran until 1964. The collection contains typescripts, oral history transcripts, correspondence, clippings, government reports, photographs, and some ephemera and research notes and materials that document Grace and Max Granich's involvement with the Communist Party and Higley Hill Camp.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John McDermott, 1991. Additional material was donated by Gina Luria Walker in 2001. Mailing list (1998), alumni newsletter, and letter (1971) donated by Marion Nestle, 2008. Additional donation of clippings, photographs, and Rewi Alley materials by Eugene and Vera Donefer in 2012. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1991.006, 1991.012, 2012.084 and NPA.2003.073.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Grace (b. Maul) Granich (1895-1971) was a key administrative figure in the national office of the Communist Party, USA (CPUSA) from 1930 to 1945, serving as secretary to CPUSA General Secretary Earl Browder and as a member of the Organization Department. On behalf of the CPUSA and the Communist International (Comintern), she traveled to the Soviet Union in 1930-1931, and in 1935-1937, to Shanghai, China, where she served as a liaison to Chinese radicals, notably Agnes Smedley. She also edited The Voice of China (her husband Max Granich was its publisher), the organ of the League for National Salvation, headed by Mme. Sun Yat Sen. During World War II she headed Intercontinent News, a CPUSA news agency, and served as a foreign agent for Service Universel de Presse (Moscow).
Max (Manny) Granich (1896-1987) was the younger brother of writer Michael Gold (b. Itzok Granich). He joined the Industrial Workers of the World in 1917, participating in several agricultural organizing campaigns in California. He joined the Communist Party sometime in the late 1920s, married Grace Maul and accompanied her to Soviet Union, where he did engineering work, and to China. Upon their return, he served as chauffeur and bodyguard for Earl Browder, and (through 1942) as Managing Editor of China Today. Following the postwar expulsion of Earl Browder, the Graniches distanced themselves from the CPUSA and in 1946 founded Higley Hill Camp (Wilmington, Vermont), a left-wing summer camp for children, which they ran until 1964. Grace Granich died in an automobile accident in 1971. In the 1970s, Max Granich was active in the Chinese-American Friendship Association and led tours to the People's Republic of China. In the early 1980s, he recorded a lengthy oral history and began work on a memoir. He died in 1987.
Related Archival Materials at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Archives
Higley Hill Camp Records (TAM.447 )
Peter Hall Higley Hill Camp Photographs (PHOTOS 239)
Marion Nestle Higley Hill Camp Photographs (PHOTOS 239)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains typescripts, oral history transcripts, correspondence, clippings, government reports, photographs, and some ephemera and research notes and materials. There is an autobiographical typescript by Grace Granich, approximately 100 pp., largely concerned with her experiences in China (along with a three-page outline of a planned autobiography covering her entire life). There is also a transcript of an oral history interview with Max Granich (607 pp.), covering his life through the 1970s, and a combined typescript-transcript, apparently the beginnings of a memoir. Shanghai police and U.S. Consular and State Department reports document the Graniches' China activities. The correspondence principally covers Grace Granich's World War II press work, much of it concerned with her registration as a foreign agent for Service Universel de Presse (Moscow), including numerous telegrams to/from Moscow; their time at and the administration of Higley Hill Camp (including letters from Herbert Aptheker and Pete Seeger); and their trips to Mexico. Other Higley Hill materials include research notes and correspondence by Higley Hill alumna Gina Luria Walker for a proposed autobiographical memoir, approximately 75 black and white photographs of the camp and campers, and ephemera and memorabilia. There is also a small amount of material related to the writer and poet Rewi Alley, who was a CPUSA member and a friend of Grace and Max when they lived in Shanghai to edit and publish Voice of China.
Transcripts.; Typescripts; Communism -- China.; Photographs.; Women communists -- United States.; Printed ephemera.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Oral histories (literary works); Notes.; Communism -- United States.; Telegrams; Reports.; Granich, Max, 1896-1987; Service Universel de Presse (Moscow, Soviet Union); Russian News Agency; Communist Party of the United States of America; Alley, Rewi, 1897-1987; Higley Hill Camp (Wilmington, Vt.); Granich, Grace, 1895-1971; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973; Smedley, Agnes, 1892-1950; McDermott, John; Walker, Gina Luria, 1942-; Donefer, Eugene; Donefer, Vera; Nestle, Marion
- Alley, Rewi, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical, 1927-1929, 1952, 1972-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- China: Shanghai Municipal Police Reports, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- China: US Government Reports (Consulate General, State Department), 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings, 1927-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1965-1968, 1971-1972, 1982-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence: Granich, Carl (son), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: Foreign Agent Registration, 1942-1944, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence: Intercontinent News Service, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: Mexico, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: RUNAG (Russian News Agency) - via cable, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence: SUPRESS (Service Universel de Presse) - via cable, ca.1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Granich, Grace: Autobiographical Typescript, ca.1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Granich, Manny: Autobiographical Typescript (based upon oral history interview) - approx. 150 pp., ca.1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Granich, Manny: Oral History Transcript, pp. 1-150, ca.1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Granich, Manny: Oral History Transcript, pp. 151-300, ca.1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Granich, Manny: Oral History Transcript, pp. 301-450, ca.1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Granich, Manny: Oral History Transcript, pp. 451-607, ca.1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Higley Hill Camp Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Higley Hill Camp Correspondence, 1954-1964, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Higley Hill Camp Ephemera, ca.1954-1960, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Higley Hill Camp Photographs, undated (Box 2)
- Higley Hill Camp: Walker, Gina Luria - Correspondence and Research Material, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Photographs: Portraits, Family, Nature Scenes, and Photographs by Tina Modotti, 1920s, undated (Box 3)